Guide to the James R. Mellow Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- October 2007 Acquisition, 1940s-1999; 3; 10.37; (16 boxes)
  - Research and Writing Files, circa 1965-1999
    - Charmed Circle: Gertrude Stein & Company
      - Hoet Henry, 1989 (Box 42)
      - Stein Travel Articles, 1980 (Box 42)
      - Gertrude Stein: The American Collection by Gail Stavitsky, 1990 (Box 42)
      - Gertrude Stein manuscript, 1980 (Box 42)
      - "Stein in DCB Extra Copies" (Box 42)
  - Other Writings, circa 1969-1998
    Included are lectures, book reviews and files relating to Mellow's art criticism and other research projects.
    - Gloucester Lecture (Box 43)
    - Library Luncheon Early Draft (Box 43)
    - Grolier Lecture (Box 43)
    - Lecture Materials, circa 1994 (Box 43)
    - Unitarian Church, 1994 (Box 43)
    - Yale Talk - July 20, 1995 / Clinton Library - 3/11/96, 1995-1996 (Box 43)
    - Mellow MLA Talk, 1987 (Box 43)
    - Tribute to Leslie George Kayz and other material, 1997-1998 (Box 43)
    - Albertus Magnus Talk, 1989 (Box 43)
    - "Am. Antiquarian Lecture and Wesleyan Correspondence", circa 1985 (Box 43)
    - Lecture UCONN Storrs; Wesleyan Reading (Box 43)
    - Leslie & Jane Katz (Box 43)
    - Albertus Magnus, 1989 (Box 43)
    - Notes on Biography, 1985 (Box 43)
    - Paris Trip 1994 Lecture (Box 43)
    - MLA (Box 43)
    - Talk Paris, 1994 (Box 43)
    - Northeastern and Personal Correspondence, 1987-1996 (Box 43)
    - Japan-America Forum 11, 1970 (Box 43)
    - Book reviews and advertisements (Box 43)
    - Borchardt (Box 43)
    - The New York Times - Book Reviews (Box 43)
    - American Craft (Box 43)
    - ARTnews Reviews (Box 43)
    - Art Digest (Box 43)
    - Art International (Box 43)
    - Le Artii Reviews (Box 43)
    - Book World (Box 43)
    - Washington Post Book World (Box 43)
    - Trova, circa 1988 (Box 43)
    - The New Republic (Box 43)
    - Commonweal, 1969 (Box 43)
    - New Criterion (Box 43)
    - International Herald Tribune, 1970 (Box 43)
    - London Times Famous Authors, 1985-1989 (Box 43)
    - Metropolitan Home - Christenberry, 1990 (Box 43)
    - "I Remember" (Box 43)
    - Book Review of Sellers on Peale, 1970 (Box 43)
    - Magazine Article Clipping (Box 43)
    - Sunrine, the Lamp, Commonweal (Box 43)
    - Commonweal, 3 (Box 43)
    - Test Exhibit Study May 1979 (Box 44)
    - Van Gogh in Arles: Study at Met. Museum of art, 1985 (Box 44)
    - Ferdinand Boesch Photo (Box 44)
    - Geoffrey Clements Photo (Box 44)
    - Photos, especially MoMA exhibit, 1968-1970 (Box 44)
    - Perls Gallery- Guggenheim Museum Photos (Box 44)
    - Industrial Design photos (Box 44)
    - Miscellaneous Photos (Box 44)
    - Montreal Expo 1967 (Box 44)
    - MoMA Photos (Box 44)
    - MoMA Exhibition, circa 1969 (Box 44)
    - MoMA 1969 Exhibition and other material (Box 44)
    - Walker Evans Bibliography, 1995 (Box 44)
    - Smithsonian Correspondence and photographs (Box 44)
    - ELC Photos (Box 44)
    - Contact Sheets and Walker Evans Bibliography (Box 44)
    - Gail Stavitsky Catalogs (Box 44)
    - Loose Photographs - 1969 Exhibit (Box 44)
    - Marlborough-Gerson Gallery Photographs and Notes (Box 44)
    - Republic of Washington Square (Box 44)
    - Greenwich Village (Box 44)
    - Serena (Box 44)
    - Greenwich Village: Annotated Copy and notes, 1992; 2 (Box 44)
    - Manuscripts Early Stories: Rejections (Box 44)
    - Gertrude Stein Reviews, drafts and congratulations., 1974 (Box 44)
    - Notebook, 1985 (Box 44)
    - Princeton Notebook (Box 44)
    - Greenwich Village (Box 44)
    - Complications of the Heart, 1994 (Box 44)
    - Chumley's (Box 44)
  - Personal Papers, 1943-1997
    - Notebook, 1953-1955 (Box 45)
    - Notebook, 1955 August (Box 45)
    - Notebook, 1969 August-1973 December (Box 45)
    - Ledger Accounts, 1969-1977 (Box 45)
    - Notebook, 1974 (Box 45)
    - Notebook, circa 1987 (Box 45)
    - Notebook and Obituaries, 1989-1997 (Box 45)
    - Typed Journal, 1996 (Box 45)
    - Portugal Trip Notes (Box 45)
    - Travel Notebook (Box 45)
    - Personal Payroll - New York Times, 1968-1995; 7 (Box 45)
    - Mellow and Cappaccio Passports, circa 1969-1987 (Box 45)
    - Postcards (Box 45)
    - Notes for the Design Book (Box 46)
    - Proposal - Haute Savoie, Berrard (Box 46)
    - Hartley, Marsden - St. Clair (Box 46)
    - James Mellow Personal (Box 46)
    - Notebook, "Autobiography Start" (Box 46)
    - Journal, 1994 (Box 46)
    - Attendees at "Remembering James Mellow", circa 1998 (Box 46)
    - High School English Assignments, 1943 (Box 46)
    - The Beacon Gloucester High School Literary Journal, 1943 (Box 46)
    - USAAF Papers and Photographs, circa 1944-1946 (Box 46)
    - Wartime Letters (WWII), circa 1944 (Box 46)
    - NY Times Obituary, 1997 (Box 46)
    - Accounting Records, 1983 (Box 46)
    - Aer Lingus Travel Documents (Box 46)
    - Notebook, 1985-1986 (Box 46)
    - "Letters H.K.", 1962-1974 (Box 46)
    - Paris Trip Notes, 1969 (Box 46)
    - A Place Apart (Box 46)
    - Loose Draft (Box 46)
    - National Book Award, circa 1993 (Box 46)
    - Bibliography (Box 46)
    - Personal Photos, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 46)
    - Borchardt Correspondence, 1981 (Box 46)
  - Printed Material
    - The New Yorker - Hemingway Review, 1992 (Box 46)
    - Entertainment Weekly - Hemingway Review, 1992 (Box 46)
    - Living with the Minotaur, Michelangelo (Box 47)
    - Eastern Review, 1980 November
    - Arts clippings (Box 47)
    - The Columbia Forum, Winter 1974 (Box 47)
    - Gourmet Magazine, November 1980; 2 (Box 47)
    - Harper's Bazaar, November 1983 (Box 47)
    - Industrial Design, March 1968-July/August 1968; 2 (Box 47)
    - The Metropolitan Museum of Art Annual Report, 1977-78, 1978
    - The New Republic, March 1975 (Box 47)
    - The New York Times Magazine, circa 1972-1980
    - People Weekly, February 1996 (Box 47)
    - Saturday Review clippings, 1980 (Box 47)
    - Wilson Quarterly, Autumn 1980 (Box 47)
    - Wisdom: The Magazine of Knowledge and Education, June 1958
    - Architectural Digest, October 1982-April 1996; 1 (Box 47)
    - Architectural Digest, October 1982-April 1996; 9 (Box 48)
  - Objects
    - Leather "Treasure Chest" Case, undated (Box 49)
      The case is annotated. It originally held letters which have been removed and placed within the Correspondence series.
    - Electric candlestick and lightbulb, undated (Box 49)
  - Oversize
    - A Life Without Consequences, author's marked set (from Research and Writing Files), circa 1992 (Box 50)
    - A Life Without Consequences, master proofs (from Research and Writing Files), circa 1992 (Box 51)
    - Wisdom: The Magazine of Knowledge and Education (from Printed Material), June 1958 (Box 52)
    - The New York Times Magazine (from Printed Material), circa 1972-1980; 3 (Box 52)
    - The New York Times Magazine (from Printed Material), circa 1972-1980; 3 (Box 53)